Guide to the Pinkerton Detective Agency Danbury Fires Investigation Collection MS 020
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Pinkerton's National Detective Agency - Danbury "Firebug" Investigation Collection
1891
MS 020
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
0.5 Linear feet
The Pinkerton Detective Agency was hired by the City of Danbury to help solve a rash of arson cases that had begun in 1888. There are 18 written reports from the Pinkerton Operative and statements the were taken by the operative from firemen, citizens, witnesses and suspects.
City of Danbury, Conn..
Provenance
Accessioned in 1976.
The reports were rescued by WestConn professors Truman Warner and Herb Janick and some student volunteers around 1970. Janick and Warner had been notified that items were being disposed of at Danbury’s old City Hall and that anything disposed of was for the taking. Janick and Warner gathered some of their students and went to City Hall to salvage what they could. According to one of the students involved in this operation, Randy Potter found the Pinkerton reports and statements folded and packed into a shoebox and showed them to Janick. Janick saw to it they were added to the collections at WestConn.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. Digital copies available and in the preferable means of access.
Historical/Biographical Note
From the summer of 1888 to February 1891 (and two fires in April of 1893), Danbury was plagued by a series of fires started by person or persons dubbed by the press: the "Firebug." The city sought help outside the Police Department to look into the case. Operative McM (John T. McManus) from Pinkerton's National Detective Agency in New York was hired by Joseph M. Ives of the City of Danbury from January 9 to February 5, 1891.
The "firebug" from 1888-1893 caused the modern equivalent of tens of millions of dollars of damage in Danbury and in such close proximity were many of the fires that there was an area dubbed to be the "firebug" district. There were many potential sources of animosity that may have motivated an arsonist but the identity of the perpetrator(s) will likely never be determined.
During the rash of arson cases (or incendiarism as it was usually called then) from 1888-1893, there were many who believed that it was the formation of a professional municipal fire department which had motivated the "Firebug." Many believed the perpetrator(s) belonged to one of the volunteer fire companies. The fires coincided with Danbury's transition from a borough to a city in 1889. Danbury followed cities like San Francisco, Baltimore St. Louis and Patterson, NJ and moved to adopt a paid department shortly after becoming a city. In late 1890, a huge fire had been deliberately set that destroyed the Foster Brothers factory and Chief Engineer Meyers' DFD was blamed for mismanagement of the fire. The Common Council had called a Special Committee to consider censure of the Fire Department and asked for Meyers' resignation. Hearings were held, firemen resigned en masse ostensibly for higher wages, and fires kept occurring. At that point, the Common Council hired a Pinkerton operative but there is no documentation of what specifically the operative was hired to do.
Morris Meyers, John Ellwood, Captain Keating, "Nasty" Gaylord, "Whiskey" Davis, Howard Stevens, Mayor Hopkins, among others were important characters in the story of the Danbury "Firebug."
Scope and Content Note
Pinkerton operative McManus’s (aka McM) 17 handwritten and (1 typescript transcription) to Joseph M. Ives on the Board of Aldermen can be found in folders 3 through 19. Individual statements from firemen, suspects, and witnesses as to their general knowledge of the fires can be found in folders 1 and 2.
Persons providing statements include: Ellwood, John H (volunteer firemen).; Bradley, David (police officer); Meyers, Morris (chief engineer DFD) x 2; Stevens, Howard (fmr firefighter, volunteer, and suspect) x 2; McCarty, Patrick (witness, ex-con); Brady, Terence (witness); Scanlon, James (witness); Darragan, Edward (witness); Bartram, William (witness); Mead, Silas (witness); and an anonymous letter addressed to Alderman G. Mortimer Rundle.
Chief Meyers, a Democrat, in his first statement identifies a key conflict that existed between him Republican and Former Chief Ellwood.
McManus also wrote daily reports that reference these statements and are viewable in the next section. In his reports, McM mentions more statements being taken than are here included. Conspicuously missing are statements that he reportedly took from Mayor Hopkins, Capt. Keating, Sgt. Waggneor, Daniel McCreedy and James Preston, among a couple others. The reports provide an interesting look at the lives many of the working men and idlers of the time.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: Statements and reports
Bartram, William.; Bradley, David.; Brady, Terence.; Darragan, Edward.; Ellwood, John H.; Ives, Joseph M.; McCarty, Patrick.; McManus, John T.; Mead, Silas.; Meyers, Morris.; Pinkerton's National Detective Agency.; Scanlon, James.; Stevens, Howard Porter; Arson investigation.; Danbury (Conn.); Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Reports.
- I. Statements
  - Morris Meyers Statement, Jan 15, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    7 pgs
  - John Ellwood Statement, Jan 16, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - David Bradley Statement, Jan 16, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    2 pgs
  - Bert Contrell Statement, Jan 17, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Howard Stevens Statement, Jan 21, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    5 pgs
  - Morris Meyers Statement # 2, Jan 18, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Howard Stevens Statement #2, Jan 22, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    3pgs
  - Patrick McCarty Statement, Jan 22, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James Flinn Statement, Jan 25, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edward Darragan Statement, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    3 pgs
  - Terrence Brady Statement, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Terrence Brady Statement, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - M. Parker Statement, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James Scanlon Statement, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1 pg
  - William Bartram Statement, Jan 31, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Silas Mead Statement, Feb 3, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous Letter, Jan 21, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- II. Reports
  - Report, Jan 13, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    12 pgs
  - Report (typescript transcription of Jan 13, 1891 report) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    9 pgs
  - Report, Jan 17, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report, Jan 19, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    6 pgs
  - Report, Jan 21, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Report, Jan 22, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report, Jan 23, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report, Jan 24, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    10 pgs
  - Report, Jan 26, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Report, Jan 28, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report, Jan 30, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report, Jan 31, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report, Jan 31, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    4 pgs
  - Report, Feb 3, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Report, Feb 4, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Report, Feb 4, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Report, Feb 5, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 19)